Guide to the Rust Engineering Company Records, 1905-1989 AIS.2006.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- President's Office Files, 1920-1929; IV.
  This series documents Rust Engineering's efforts to establish itself in Pittsburgh and its eventual prosperity during the Roaring Twenties. In 1920, the Rust Engineering partnership was dissolved and the company was incorporated into three functionally separate entities; the Rust Engineering Company of Delaware (Pittsburgh office), headed by S.M. Rust, the Rust Engineering Company of Maryland (Washington, D.C. office) and the Rust Engineering Company of Alabama (Birmingham office). Each company took jobs in its respective region and functioned independently from the others, but S.M. Rust was president of Rust Engineering as a whole and received reports from all offices. During the mid-1920s, the Maryland company was dissolved and transferred its assets to Pittsburgh, becoming a branch specializing in sales for the Pittsburgh office.
  Much of the correspondence from the early 1920s concerns problems with particular jobs and attempts to correct them. Although some of the delays were related to weather conditions and railway strikes, problems were most often attributed to personnel; there is much discussion of habits and character as they apply to work, and the letters are surprisingly emotional and dynamic, but also fair. Other conversations concern orders and shipments, salaries and wages, attempts to land desirable jobs, and occasional run-ins with unions, particularly Pittsburgh Bricklayers Union No. 2. A series of letters between all three brothers, placed in a folder labeled "hard times," discusses the strain of financial difficulties on both the company and the family.
  Despite the hardship, Rust Engineering took many jobs, especially to install boilers and build complete power houses and incinerators. In 1925, the company hired experienced chimney engineer Eric Plagwit and formed the Chimney Division, which would go on to erect more than 3,000 concrete and brick industrial chimneys. Rust's Furnace Division, which specialized in the design and installation of large furnaces for heating steel and other metals, became a wholly-owned subsidiary in 1927 and thrived from then on. More information about the Rust Furnace Division can be found in Series VII.
  - Correspondence, 1.
    Items in this subseries are not in original order, but have been filed chronologically by month. When exchanges covering several months were found together, they were filed by the date of the earliest letter. In addition to general correspondence, there are also files of letters between the Pittsburgh office and other branch offices. These interoffice files are present throughout the rest of the collection.
    - S.M. Rust correspondence regarding incorporation, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence between S.M. Rust and E.M. Rust, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1921 (Box 12, Folder 02-04)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1922 (Box 12, Folder 05-08)
    - "Hard Times" correspondence between Rust brothers, 1922 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1923 (Box 13, Folder 02-03)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1924 (Box 13, Folder 04-05)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-August 1925 (Box 13, Folder 06-07)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, September-December 1925 (Box 14, Folder 01-02)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1926 (Box 14, Folder 03-06)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1927 (Box 15, Folder 01-04)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1927 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1927 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1928 (Box 16, Folder 01-04)
    - Washington, D.C. Office correspondence, 1928 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1928 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1929 (Box 16, Folder 07-10)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1929 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1929 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Washington Office correspondence, 1929 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Abstracts of New York mail, 1925-1927 (Box 17, Folder 04-06)
    - Personal mail and trade articles, 1920-1929 (Box 17, Folder 07-08)
  - Job Files, 2.
    Job files contain documents related to the acquisition of jobs, such as proposals and contracts, as well as folders on individual jobs filed alphabetically by client name. More information about these jobs, as well as those which did not receive their own folders, can be found in the correspondence files. The type of work, location, job number, and dates have been included where possible
    - Inquiries handled by New York Office, 1925-1926 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Inquiry reports, interoffice, 1926 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Inquiries and proposals for boilers and furnaces, 1927-1928 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Prospect reports, 1928 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Proposal file, 1928-1929 (Box 17, Folder 13-14)
    - List of foremen, 1928 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Chimney contracts, c1925 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Contract reports, 1926-1929 (Box 18, Folder 02-04)
    - American State Bank, office building at Grant & Sixth, Pittsburgh, PA (Job #101), 1927-1928 (Box 18, Folder 05-06)
    - Balmer Company, incinerator, Floral Park, NY, 1925 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Ford Motor Company, manufacturing plant, Chester, PA (Job #1600), 1926-1931 (Box 18, Folder 08-09)
    - Davison Coke & Iron Company, cement plant, Neville Island, PA (Job #2150), 1928-1929 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Delaware River Steel Company, blast furnace, Chester, PA (Job #1797), 1927 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Henry Clay Hotel Company, 8-story hotel building, Ashland, KY (Job # 1828), 1927 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Koppers Construction Company, Koppers Building, Pittsburgh, PA, 1927-1928 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Koppers Construction Company, Koppers Building, Pittsburgh, PA, 1927-1929 (Box 19, Folder 01-03)
    - Koppers Seaboard By-Product Coke Company, office buildings at Waverly, NJ and Clifton, NJ, 1929 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Koppers Seaboard Company, office building, Kearny, NJ, 1929 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Koppers Seaboard Co., office building, Jamaica Yard, NY (Job #2370), 1929 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Published plan for Koppers Construction Co. By-Product Recovery Plant, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, boiler settings, Van Nest, NJ (Job #2192), 1929 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Packard Motor Car Company, contract for additions to a building, Pittsburgh, PA (Job #104), 1928 (Box 19, Folder 09-11)
    - Phoenix Utility Company, chimneys, Trinidad, TX, 1925 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Raleigh-Wyoming Coal Company, construction work, Glen Rogers, WV (Job # 1227), 1921 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - U.S. Government, addition to a government printing office, Washington, D.C., 1928-1929 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - YMCA, building, Newell, PA (Job #102), 1928 (Box 20, Folder 03-04)
  - Subject Files, 3.
    There are several files related to the dissolution of the partnership and creation of the three companies, as well as information about Rust's attempts to purchase brick plants.
    - Dissolution of Partnership, 1920 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Annual meetings and stocks, 1920-1924 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - J.B. Mingle vs. Rust Engineering, 1921 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Agreements with other companies, 1922 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Expenses related to International Bricklayers and Plasterers Union Local #2,June 17, 1922 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Annual report of Washington, D.C. Office, 1923 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Financial information, 1923-1928 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Receipted invoices, 1924-1926 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - New Hope Brick Company, purchase of plant, 1925 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - John Fenson Company, sales, 1925-1926 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - Applications for a construction executive position, 1926 (Box 20, Folder 15-16)
    - Cumberland Brick Company: lease, 1926 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Potomac Fire Brick Company; purchase of plant, 1926 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Valley Fruit Company vs. Rust Engineering, 1926 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Report of profits and losses, 1926 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - International Cement Corporation, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Portable boiler, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Proposed purchase of brick plant, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Discussion on Piercing Mill Furnace Design, August 7, 1928 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Patent: Method of and Apparatus for Supporting the Side Walls of Excavations, 1928 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Proposed Chimney Builders Association, 1928 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Report of profits and losses, 1928 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Woodbridge Property for brick manufacturing, 1928-1929 (Box 21, Folder 12-13)
    - Letters of recommendation by S.M. Rust, 1928-1930 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Drawings, Study for River-Rail Terminal, February, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 15)
- President's Office Files, 1930-1939; V.
  The stock market crash of October 29, 1929, impacted Rust Engineering as it did nearly all businesses. Correspondence from this time shows that in the early 1930s, the company was forced to let many employees go and cut the salaries of most others, often more than once. S.M. Rust pulled funds from his personal savings to secure loans. Rust Engineering survived the hardship through its versatility, taking on any jobs, large or small, that it could secure.
  In 1936, the National Recovery Administration's (NRA) "codes of fair competition" became a major concern for Rust Engineering and many other corporations. Part of Roosevelt's New Deal to restore the economy and pull the nation out of depression, NRA codes were intended to discourage aggressive competition by setting minimum wages and maximum hours for workers. Following the codes was not required by law, but public boycotts of companies that could not display the Blue Eagle symbol of compliance pressured businesses to conform. Rust Engineering was affected by a number of codes, and fearing that the cuts were too drastic and could severely impair the company's ability to function, E.M. Rust of the Washington office formed a committee to have certain exceptions made under the constructor's code. He argued that "engineering constructors", which handle both design work and construction, operate differently than pure construction companies and required different rules. The NRA code files contain correspondence and other documents that trace these efforts, which were ultimately successful.
  During the 1930s, S.M. Rust, Jr. worked closely with his father and became operating manager in 1939. S.M. Rust, Sr., still president, began building his estate "Murray Hill" in Leesburg, Virginia, and had his son and other officers send daily reports to keep track of office activity. After 1939, the files become primarily those of S.M.Rust, Jr.
  - Correspondence, 1.
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1930 (Box 22, Folder 01-04)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1930 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1930 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Washington, D.C. Office correspondence, 1930 (Box 22, Folder 07-08)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1931 (Box 22, Folder 09-10)
    - Correspondence between S.M. Rust and C.F. Drew, 1931 (Box 23, Folder 01-02)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1931 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1931 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Washington, D.C. Office correspondence, 1931 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-August 1932 (Box 23, Folder 06-08)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, September-December 1932 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence between S.M. Rust and C.F. Drew, 1932 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1932 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1932 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia Office correspondence, 1932-1939 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Washington, D.C. Office correspondence, 1932 (Box 24, Folder 06-07)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1933 (Box 24, Folder 08-09)
    - Correspondence between S.M. Rust and C.F. Drew, 1933 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1933 (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1933 (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Washington, D.C. Office correspondence, 1933 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Washington, D.C. Office correspondence -- E.M. Rust, 1933 (Box 25, Folder 02-03)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1934 (Box 25, Folder 04-07)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1934 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1934 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Washington, D.C. Office correspondence, 1934 (Box 25, Folder 10-11)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1935 (Box 26, Folder 01-02)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1935 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1935 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Washington, D.C. Office correspondence, 1935 (Box 26, Folder 05-07)
    - S.M. Rust Day File, January-December 1935 (Box 26, Folder 08-10)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1936 (Box 27, Folder 01-04)
    - Correspondence between S.M. Rust and C.F. Drew, 1936 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1936 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Chicago Office correspondence, 1936 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1936 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Washington, D.C. Office correspondence, 1936 (Box 27, Folder 09-12)
    - S.M. Rust Day File, January-December 1936 (Box 28, Folder 01-04)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-December 1937 (Box 28, Folder 05-07)
    - Interoffice correspondence, 1937 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1937 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Chicago Office correspondence, 1937 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1937 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Washington, D.C. Office correspondence, 1937 (Box 29, Folder 04-06)
    - S.M. Rust Day File, January-February 1937 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - S.M. Rust Day File, March-December 1937 (Box 30, Folder 01-05)
    - S.M. Rust Correspondence, 1938 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - S.M. Rust Correspondence, 1938 (Box 31, Folder 01-02)
    - S.M. Rust Day File, January-September 1938 (Box 31, Folder 03-07)
    - S.M. Rust Day File, October-December 1938 (Box 32, Folder 01-02)
    - General Day File, March-December 1938 (Box 32, Folder 03-09)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, March-April 1938 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, May-December 1938 (Box 33, Folder 01-03)
    - Chicago Office correspondence, 1938 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1938 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Washington, D.C. Office correspondence, 1938 (Box 33, Folder 06-07)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - S.M. Rust Day File, January-August 1939 (Box 34, Folder 02-03)
    - S.M. Rust, Jr. Day File, January-December 1939 (Box 34, Folder 04-05)
    - Correspondence between S.M. Rust and C.F. Drew, 1939 (Box 34, Folder 06-07)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1939 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Birmingham Office correspondence, 1939 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - New York Office correspondence, 1939 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Personal mail and trade articles, 1930-1939 (Box 35, Folder 03-04)
  - Job Files, 2.
    Job files contain documents related to the acquisition of jobs, such as proposals and contracts, as well as folders on individual jobs filed alphabetically by client name. More information about these jobs, as well as those which did not receive their own folders can be found in the correspondence files. The type of work, location, job number, and dates have been included where possible.
    - Prospects, 1930 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Prospects handled by R.R. Cutler, 1930-1938 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Prospects handled by John English, 1931 (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Prospects handled by C.A. Sheldon, 1931-1932 (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Prospects handled by G.P. Prather, 1938 (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - Proposals, 1930 (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - Contracts, 1930-1939 (Box 35, Folder 11-13)
    - Contracts, 1938-1939 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Construction Department contracts, 1931 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Labor cost reports by contract, 1930-1931 (Box 36, Folder 03-05)
    - Bartlett Hayward Company, gas holder foundations (Job #3026) Chillum Road, MD, 1934-1935 (Box 36, Folder 06-07)
    - Charles L. Stockhausen & Co., architect, government funded apartment complex, Pittsburgh, PA, 1931 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - City of Pittsburgh, garbage incinerators, 1932 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - District of Columbia, "O" Street and Georgetown incinerators (Job #2817& 2843), Washington, D.C., 1931-1932 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - District of Columbia, district heating system (proposal by Rust), 1935 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Georgia School of Technology, School of Aeronautics, wind tunnel, Atlanta, Georgia, 1931 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Gulf Refining Company, pump house (Job #2629), Cleves, Ohio, 1931 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Guntersville Bridge blueprint (client unknown), 1938 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - H. Craig Severance, Inc., apartment house, Pittsburgh, PA, 1931 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Town of Leesburg, VA, sewage system and disposal plant, Leesburg, VA, 1935-1936 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Lehigh Valley Railroad Company, rebuilding boilers, Sayre, PA, 1930 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Lehigh Valley Railroad Company, railroad bridge (Job# 2778-9), Weequahic Park, NJ, 1932 (Box 37, Folder 08-09)
    - Pangborn Corporation, building (Job #2900), Hagerstown, MD, 1932-1934 (Box 37, Folder 10)
    - Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company, brickwork (Job #3147), Mt. Vernon, Ohio, 1935-1936 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - Southern States Cooperative Mills, grain elevator (Job #3127), Baltimore, MD, 1934 (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Tennessee Valley Authority, alterations to Tennessee River Bridge (Job #3626), Guntersville, AL, 1938 (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - Tennessee Valley Authority, blast furnace, Muscle Shoals, AL, 1934 (Box 37, Folder 14)
    - Terry Steam Turbine Company, plant, Hartford, CT, 1934 (Box 37, Folder 15)
    - Westinghouse Electric and Manufacturing Company -- warehouse, (Job #2882), Mansfield, Ohio, 1932 (Box 37, Folder 16)
    - Westvaco Chlorine Products, Inc., plant, South Charleston, WV, 1931 (Box 37, Folder 17)
    - Wheeling Steel Corporation, mill foundations (Job #3062), location unknown, 1934 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - U.S. Government (War Department), addition to Wright Field heating plant (Job #3051), Wright, Ohio, 1934-1936 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company, mill foundations (Job #3103), Youngstown, Ohio, 1934-1935 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Unknown company and project, riots at job (Job# 2776-2777), Ashland, KY, 1932 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Paper Mill Job Files, 3.
    General files on paper mill jobs are filed by year at the start of the series, while individual jobs are arranged alphabetically by company name.
    - Paper mills, multiple jobs, 1934-1937 (Box 38, Folder 05-09)
    - Paper mills, multiple jobs, 1938-1939 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Paper mill issue of The Tidewater News, 1938 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Albemarle Paper Manufacturing Company, Brooks-Scanlon Corporation -- plant, Richmond, VA, 1939 (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Brooks-Scanlon Corporation, kraft Mill, Foley, FL, 1937-1938 (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Chesapeake-Camp Paper Company contract, paper mill, Franklin, VA, 1936-1937 (Box 39, Folder 05-09)
    - Chesapeake-Camp Paper Company, paper mill, Franklin, VA, 1937-1938 (Box 40, Folder 01-02)
    - Crossett Lumber Company, kraft pulp and paper mill (Job # 3617), Crossett, AR, January-September 1936 (Box 40, Folder 03-05)
    - Crossett Lumber Company, kraft pulp and paper mill, Crossett, AR, October, 1936-January 1939 (Box 41, Folder 01-05)
    - Crossett Mill progress reports, 1937 (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Crossett Mill cost estimates, 1938 (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - Equitable Paper Bag Company, Inc., pulp mill, Orange, TX, 1936-1937 (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - Fernandina Pulp and Paper Company, pulp mill (Job #3551), Fernandina, FL, 1938-1939 (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Florida Pulp and Paper Company, pulp and paper mill (Job #3960), Pensacola, FL, c1937 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Hollingsworth & Whitney Company, paper mill, Mobile, AL, 1938-1939 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Hytest Newsprint Company, newsprint mill, Rome, GA, 1936-1937 (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Riegel Paper Company, paper and pulp mill, Acme, NC, 1938 (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - Rust Family, S.M. Rust Residence "Murray Hill", Leesburg, VA (Job #IB3598), 1939 (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - St. Joe Paper Company, paper mill, St. Joe, FL, 1936-1937 (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - Southern Kraft Corporation, recovery plant, Panama City, FL, 1930 (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Southland Paper Company, paper mill, Lufkin, TX, 1937-1938 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Subject Files, 4.
    - Patent Applications, 1930-1936 (Box 43.1, Oversize 1)
    - Blueprints and instructions for the Furnace and Chimney Divisions, 1930 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Accident reports and insurance policies, 1930 (Box 44, Folder 2)
    - Purchase of Vulcan Tile and Brick Company, 1930 (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - Patents for steam heating devices, 1930-1931 (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Financial Information handled by C.F. Drew, 1930-1937 (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Purchase of plant from Elkland Fire Brick Company, 1931 (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Articles on price fixing, wages, and economic decline, c1931 (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - Negotiations with the Pittsburgh Cut Stone Company, 1942 (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Bulletins from the Chamber of Commerce of Pittsburgh, 1932-1936 (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - Cold Metal Process Company, controlling stock, 1933-1934 (Box 44, Folder 12)
    - NRA Codes, 1933 (Box 44, Folder 13-14)
    - NRA Codes by Associated General Contractors of America, 1933 (Box 44, Folder 15)
    - NRA Codes by the Engineering Constructors Group, 1933 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - NRA Codes, 1934 (Box 45, Folder 02-04)
    - Settlement of A.H. Blair account, 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 5)
    - Birmingham Fabricating Company agreements, 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 6)
    - Purchase of Woodbridge Brick Plant, 1936-1937 (Box 45, Folder 7)
    - Sales representative in Carolinas, T.C. Heyward, 1936 (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Legal council on the Fair Labor Act of 1938 and other issues, 1938-1940 (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Purchase and management of Virginia Highlands Property, 1935-1937 (Box 45, Folder 10)
    - Masonry Chimney Association, 1936 (Box 45, Folder 11)
    - Agreements and cost sheets, undated (Box 45, Folder 12)
- President's Office Files, 1940-1949; VI.
  Even before the U.S. entered World War II, jobs became more available as the nation began building its defenses. By 1941, the company was working almost exclusively on government-funded projects across the United States. Rust Engineering's skill in building large plants made it ideal for the jobs, which included the construction of navy shipyards, machine shop and assembly buildings, shell forging and machining plants, and ordnance plants. Some projects, such as a Naval Ordnance Plant in Canton, Ohio, employed hundreds of employees and operated on 24-hour shifts. The company was particularly proud of this plant, which was completed ahead of schedule and contained what one worker called "the prettiest machine shop I ever saw."